think I have a question
it's um a seclusion is that
an activity or is that a result
of certain practice uh
uh
both depending how you look at it
so it has to start as an activity
has to start something you actively seek
but then if you practice rightly your
mind becomes secluded from
unwholesome things and that's then the
result and that's why the Buddha did say
that the true seclusion is when mind is
free from greediversion delusion not
when one is away from people
although he might be alone he still
dwells in company of central desire and
unwholesome states
but that resulting seclusion
would not just come magically if you
have not if you can't even like live
alone be by yourself at least for some
time of the day
um so so that's why you have to do it as
a practice that can then lead to the
actual seclusion
and it's kind of
a balance of both in a sense because
sometimes people
try to justify non-physical seclusion
would say well see the true seclusion is
just being free from unwholesome States
thus doesn't matter if I just spend my
days with people all day long
and then you have the other group of
people who just Cates all the people and
just wants to be alone because that's an
easier mode of existence and then they
just quote the suitors of the activity
aspect of seclusion but that aspect the
gradual training comes much later you
don't start with it if you're starting
with it there's usually something else
there some other kind of ulterior motive you
some other kind of ulterior motive you
have
yeah so so basically the the Buddhist
teaching is actually be very easily
wrongly graphs to actually enforce your
version easy
anything anything the Buddha himself
giving instruction if you're not if you
don't attempt to it rightly you'll just
use it for your own sake of your own
wrong views yeah
it's interesting in the
sitters like
it's to be content in solitude or to
Delight in seclusion
is considered quite a high achievement
achievements work just it's really work
just to get there yeah
um and
I mean one thing to consider in regard
to that is like you know if for a monk
at the at that time dwelling in solitude
wouldn't necessarily mean quite the same
thing as it would today as in it would
not just be okay I'm in a room on my own
but like whenever I want I can contact
somebody or I can you know access some
distraction or whatever it's like really
I'm in my own on a forest and
even if I want to yeah
so it's like to be content within that
environment is quite a high achievement
is quite a high achievement
yeah so it's not just like I'll go on my
own and I can do whatever I want
and you know go back and contact people
or you know wherever I want it's like
you have to kind of put yourself into
that my mental state even if you're not in
my mental state even if you're not in
this you can't you don't have to kind of
I don't know I'll go up on a mountain
and forsake everything but like into
that you know that that's
you know that that's
mental state of okay isolation
and complete isolation ultimately I mean
that's obviously then a training that
you have to work
towards difficult thing to do to Delight
in solitude but once there is a light
and Solitude the goal is quickly
achieved there's a discourse
yeah because it's the whole the whole
gradual training we talk about that's
what it leads to
delaying Solitude and it's like
preferring it
just to be literally alone even without
anything to do with it like without
anything yeah yeah of course yeah yeah
the non-activity the true non activity
yeah
which is the most
it's and it's also like the worst
punishment you can give to somebody in
the world so you put them in the
solution you can find them without any
without anything
um visible activity they can engage with
and it's just
becomes unbearable confining
when you have others around there's
There's an opportunity for
yeah distraction yeah but again like you
do have to emphasize that it's not just
something okay so I'll just train for so
that you you train by keeping the
precepts guarding the sense does don't
give your eyes to also stayed certainly
don't act out of them
and then the light in solitary will
become as a result of that then you can
actively develop further
if you're trying to jump the queue
before you have been established in the
Right View established in virtue all
those all those things that the Buddha
list to that monk they want to go in
solitude who wasn't ready well you won't
be ready you'll be going for wrong
reasons and just well they're either
with mind invested with lust or hatred
or whatever else bothers you
um
and you'll fail in that sense
and also what what can easily happen see
like people
who are whose minds are easily bothered
by side sounds male taste touches
it can kind of play into that natural
tendency to just just avoid things that bother me
to just just avoid things that bother me
oh because you know the Buddha said
seclusion is is the utmost goal so I
feel Justified then in in just sitting
my cootie not seeing not talking to
anybody not not doing anything because
the slightest act will just disturb my
mind make it filled with ill will
flooded with passion and so on
so then your seclusion becomes your
coping mechanism whereby your Super
Hyper extra sensitive even before when
you were a Layman you were not that
sensitive you could actually endure more
but now like the ticking clock is
driving me nuts the global wind the
water river I just can't bear this noise
my meditation is suffering I can't I
need to change it could I need to change
a monastery I need to change a country I
need to change a place I need to change
the place quiet earplugs soundproof room
that's not seclusion
that's absolute complete kind of um
like extreme way perversion of avoidance
avoiding things did bother you because
your view still thinks the Border comes
from those things
so you haven't even abandoned the
mundane wrong views of where the
suffering comes from
while you sit in your padded cell where
nothing can come through when you're at
peace that's not the peace
always chopping your limbs your mind
doesn't move well that's the piece yeah
elements enduring elements discomfort I
mean you can read you'd like read the
the kandaka stories around you know
vinaya and then how the monks lived the
engagement and the exposure and the
people and stuff is like
some of it was quite hectic but there
were other hunts with Supernatural
powers and stuff like that
so it's like okay so there is probably
some balance there that today's average
Buddhist would not necessarily see so
like okay so let me then start in the
right order as the Buddha described in
the gradual training
yeah you know simplify your life don't
sit the midst of a loud crowd avoid
obviously on wholesome environment but
don't get too precious about it
because it's gonna go too much the other
way and it's like you start enjoying
seclusion because you start feeding the
bother even more
because you don't know how to deal with
it
and it's like a um the dog tied around
the post tries to
get get himself free and ends up being
even more tied to the post even even
shorter leash so ultimately
so ultimately
the Border
the disturbances
doesn't it doesn't come from the world
comes from that craving comes from that
resistance so same goes with the company
so same goes with the company
and if the Mind moves
pleasantly unpleasantly
towards the company it's all because of
your own resistance towards it not
because of that person or these people
and so on
so that's where the true Solitude is
when that has been calmed and tamed and
extinguished that that movement that
craving that resistance
and that's why the Buddha said
well he's as in private so in public as
in public so in private there's no
difference his behavior does not change
there's no different reference point to
that and like the Buddha said the Target now
and like the Buddha said the Target now
he's at ease whether he's an assembly of
the gods or Villages one person thousand
nothing changes in terms of his mental
composure
so that's the true solitude
so it's more in regard to
how dramas are usually described
basically seclusion from an ocean state
yeah but to see what those are
it's beneficial to go into physical seclusion
beneficial to go into physical seclusion
so or kind of as I say decrease
the intensity of um
things around the world yeah yeah so
that you can see these things and the
step the necessity of going into
physical seclusion that we ourselves
talked about in the past many times
comes after
you have been taming your senses
properly thoroughly not giving rise to
an awesome state which comes after
you've been thoroughly established in
virtue and presets
not like over a weekend or something and
now you're going to go into seclusion so
that by the end of the week you enter
Jannah so becoming established in precepts well
so becoming established in precepts well
how many years have you spent not being
established in presets so
divided by half
depending on your app for the give or
take it's the previous line
so it's going to take a while for that
mind to tame
sure you're gonna have
minor releases so to speak insights and
so on but
it's not a race really
like oh I'll just do this if it is it's
because you're still acting out of your
craving because well whether I get it or not
because well whether I get it or not
it's still a preferable mode of
existence taming and sense restraint is factually
taming and sense restraint is factually
better
even according to your own Central
values the only reason people attend sensuality
the only reason people attend sensuality
is because it hurts if they don't so
first you're touched by pain that's why
then you seek delight and pleasure and
so on and and and that's why you would
not you would also want to not be
touched by that pain in the first place
so if you tame your senses the desires
will fade
the pressures will lessen and you'll be
factually more content and happier
so you need like 80 physical seclusion
not hundred percent
pointing
and so just so that you have a basis for
seeing your mind
having things calmed down
so it's like this like this Monastery is
a probably like an 80 physical seclusion
place so that you can actually do the try and
so that you can actually do the try and
get into the real Solitude yeah of 100
mental seclusion well that's the thing
the real solitary will be that mental
yeah so there is no like 100 physical
Solitude I mean you can aim for it but
that means you're overshooting the mark
now yeah you know there are empty rooms
empty Huts empty roots of a tree go
their monks and and and contemplate
things basically so
as I said there is a somebody who starts
that way can become too precious but it
won't be hard to see if you're honest
that that preciousness comes from oh I
don't want to be bothered
like I resisted I I'm I'm averse to the
idea of
so that's why I'm secluded it's like
well no then I should be bothered
not by something terribly unwholesome
but by duties or answering a question
and so on
but well if that bothers me
when the body starts breaking a path and
illnesses and hospitals and so on my
practice will go out of the window
because I've been practicing it on a
wrong field that's not where you play
this